So, without romanticizing this too much:
بدون تجميل صورة هذا الأمر كثيرًا:
imagine that you light your home with kerosene and candles every night,
تخيلوا أنكم تضيئون منازلكم باستخدام الكيروسين والشموع كل ليلة،
and that you do all of your cooking
وأنكم تطهون كل طعامكم
with charcoal.
باستخدام الفحم.
This is how the world's two billion poorest people
فهذا ما يفعله ملياري إنسان الأكثر فقرًا عبر العالم،
cook and light their homes every day.
هكذا يطهون ويضيئون منازلهم كل يوم.
This isn't just inconvenient,
هذا الأمر ليس مزعجاً فحسب،
this is inefficient,
لكنه غير فعال،
it's expensive,
باهظ الثمن،
it's harmful to human health, harmful to the environment,
يؤذي صحة الإنسان، يضر بالبيئة،
and it's unproductive.
وهذا غير مثمر.
And that's energy poverty.
وهذا هو فقر الطاقة.
So let me give you a couple of examples.
لذا دعوني أعطيكم مثالين.
I work in Haiti,
أعمل في (هايتي)،
where about 80% of the population lives in energy poverty.
حيث يعاني ما يقرب من 80% من السكان من فقر الطاقة.
The average household spends 10% of its income
ينفق البيت العادي 10% من الدخل
on kerosene for lighting –
على الكيروسين من أجل الإضاءة،
that's an order of magnitude greater than what the average US household spends
أكثر مما تنفقه أسرة أمريكية عادية
on electricity to light their homes.
لإضاءة المنزل بالكهرباء.
The 2008 hurricane season in Haiti caused
تسبب موسم الأعاصير في (هايتي)
about one billion dollars in damage.
في دمار يقدَّر بمليار دولار.
That was a sixth of their GDP.
ما يعادل سُدس الناتج المحلي الإجمالي.
The damage was so severe
كان أثر الدمار بالغًا،
because the primary energy fuel in Haiti is charcoal,
لأن وقود الطاقة الرئيسي في (هايتي) هو الفحم.
which is made from trees,
الذي يصنع من الأشجار،
and has left the country almost completely deforested.
وجرّد البلاد من غاباتها تمامًا.
Without trees, the country can't absorb heavy rains and massive flooding,
بدون أشجار، لا تستطيع البلاد استيعاب الأمطار الغزيرة والفيضانات الشديدة،
as a result.
كنتيجة لذلك.
So in the industrialized world,
في العالم الصناعي،
we built walls that protect us from the externalities of our energy use;
نبني جدراناً تحمينا من العوامل الخارجية جراء استخدامنا للطاقة؛
we can afford to clean up acute environmental disasters;
نجحنا في تجاوز تبعات الكوارث البيئية الشديدة،
and we can also afford to adapt to chronic conditions
وفي التكيف مع المشاكل البيئية المتكررة،
like climate change.
مثل تغير المناخ.
That's not the case for Haiti. They can't afford this.
هذا ليس هو الحال في (هايتي). لا يستطيعون تحمل تكلفة هذا.
The only way they're going to lift themselves out of energy poverty
الحل الوحيد لتجاوز مشكل فقر الطاقة
is by adapting fuels that are more efficient,
هو استخدام أنواع الوقود الأكثر فعالية،
that are less expensive,
الأقل تكلفة،
that are better for human health, better for the environment
الأفضل للصحة وللبيئة
and that are more productive.
والأكثر إنتاجية.
So it turns out that those fuels and technologies exist,
لذا اتضح أن هذه الأنواع من الوقود والتكنولوجيا موجودة،
and this is an example of that.
وإليكم مثال عن هذا.
This is a solar LED lightbulb
هذا مصباح (ليد) يعمل بالطاقة الشمسية
that we sell for a retail price of about 10 dollars in rural Haiti.
الذي نبيعه بالتقسيط ب10 دولارات في ريف (هايتي).
That's a payback period of less than three months
مدة صلاحيته تقل عن 3 أشهر
for the average Haitian household.
بالنسبة لأسرة متوسطة الحال في (هايتي).
The prescriptions to solve energy poverty seems pretty straightforward:
فالوسيلة لحل مشكل فقر الطاقة تبدو واضحة جدًا:
you develop these technologies that have a great return on investment,
العمل على تطوير هذه التكنولوجيا التي لها عائد كبير في الاستثمار،
and people should be snatching them up.
وينبغي أن يقتنصها الناس.
But that's not the case.
لكن هذه ليس ما يحدث.
The first time I ever went down to Haiti was in August of 2008,
المرة الأولى التي ذهبت فيها إلى (هايتي) كانت في أغسطس 2008،
sort of on a whim,
كانت نوعًا ما للترفيه،
and I was fielding surveys in the rural south of the country
وكنت أجري دراسات ميدانية في الريف جنوب البلاد
to assess the extent of energy poverty.
لتقييم حجم فقر الطاقة.
And at night, I would go around sometimes
وفي الليل، كنت أذهب بالجوار أحيانًا
and I would speak with the street vendors
وأتحدث مع الباعة المتجولين
and see if they were interested in buying these solar LED lamps.
وأرى إن كانوا مهتمين بشراء هذه المصابيح.
One woman who I encountered turned down my offer,
قابلتني امرأة رفضت عرضي،
and she said, “Mon chéri, c'est trop Cher,”
وقالت: “,Mon chéri, c'est trop Cher"
which basically means, “My dear, it's too expensive.”
وتعني "عزيزي، هذا باهظ الثمن،"
But I tried to explain to her,
لكني حاولت أن أشرح لها،
“Look, this is going to save you a lot of money,
"انظري، هذا سيوفر لك الكثير من المال،
and it's going to give you even better light
وسيعطيكِ إضاءة أفضل بكثير
than what you're using now with the kerosene.”
من تلك التي تستخدمينها بالكيروسين."
So I didn't make the sale,
لم أنجح في البيع،
but I did learn a really important lesson,
لكني تعلمت درسًا مهمًا للغاية،
which is that technology, products,
أن تلك التكنولوجيا والمنتجات
were not going to end energy poverty.
لن تُنهي فقر الطاقة.
Instead, access was going to.
بدلًا من ذلك، ما سينهيه هو إمكانية الوصول.
Specifically, there are two types of access
تحديدًا، هناك نوعان من طرق الوصول
that are going to end energy poverty:
اللذان سينهيان فقر الطاقة:
there's physical access, and there's financial access.
هناك وصول بدني، ووصول مالي.
So, physical access --
أما عن الوصول البدني،
what does that mean?
ماذا يعني ذلك؟
It's very expensive for low-income households in developing countries
هذا باهظ الثمن للأسر محدودة الدخل في الدول النامية
to reach major centers of commerce.
للوصول لمراكز التجارة الكبرى.
And it's basically impossible for them to order something off Amazon.com.
ومن غير الممكن لهم الشراء عبر موقع (أمازون).
“The last mile” is a phrase that's normally associated
"الميل الأخير" هي عبارة مرتبطة عادةً
with the telecommunications industry.
بصناعة الاتصالات السلكية واللاسلكية.
It means that last bit of wire that's necessary
هذا يعني الجزء الأخير والمهم
to connect the customer to the provider.
لربط العميل مع المزوِّد بالخدمة.
What we need for ending energy poverty are last-mile retailers
ما نحتاج لإنهاء فقر الطاقة، هو مُقَسطي الميل الأخير
that bring these clean energy products to the people.
الذين يوفرون بدائل طاقية نظيفة للسكان
The kerosene and charcoal value chains already figured this out:
أظهرت سلاسل القيمة في الكيروسين والفحم النباتي ما يلي:
those fuels are ubiquitous across the entire country.
مصادر الوقود هذه واسعة الانتشار في أرجاء البلاد.
You can go to the most remote village in Haiti
تستطيع الوصول لأبعد القرى النائية في (هايتي)
and you will find somebody selling kerosene and charcoal.
وستجد أشخاصًا يبيعون الكيروسين والفحم.
So the other type of access: financial.
والنوع الثاني من طرق الوصول هو الجانب المادي.
We all know that clean energy products, technologies,
نعلم جميعا أن منتجات الطاقة النظيفة والتكنولوجيا
tend to be characterized by higher upfront costs,
ذات تكاليف أولية عالية،
but very low operating costs.
لكن تكاليف تشغيلها قليلة.
And so in the industrialized world,
ففي الدول الصناعية،
we have very generous subsidies that are specifically designed
نحصل على الكثير من الدعم المخصص
to bring down those upfront costs.
لتخفيض هذه التكاليف الأولية.
Those subsidies don't exist in Haiti.
هذا الدعم غير موجود في (هايتي).
What they do have is microfinance.
كل ما لديهم هي تمويلات المشاريع الصغرى،
But you're going to severely diminish the value proposition
لكنك ستقلل القيمة المقترحة بشدة
of your clean energy product
لمنتجات الطاقة النظيفة
if you expect somebody in Haiti to go out, get a microloan,
إذا توقعت أن شخصًا في (هايتي) سيأخذ قرضًا صغيرًا
go back to the retailer,
ويذهب إلى بائع بالتقسيط،
and then buy the clean energy product.
ويشتري منتجات الطاقة النظيفة.
So the prescription to end energy poverty is much more complicated
باختصار، فحل مشكل فقر الطاقة أكثر تعقيداً،
than simply products.
من توفير المنتجات فحسب.
We need to integrate financial access
نحن في حاجة لدمج سبل الوصول المادية
directly into new, innovative distribution models.
مباشرةً مع حلول لتوزيع الطاقة أكثر تطوراً،
What does that mean?
ماذا يعني هذا؟
That means bundling consumer credit with the retailer.
هذا يعني تجميع الائتمان المقدَّم للمستهلك مع بائعي التقسيط.
This is really easy for Bloomingdale’s to do,
وهو أمر سهل بالنسبة لشركة (بلومينجديل)
but it's not so easy for a rural sales agent in Haiti to do.
لكن الأمر يختلف بالنسبة للتجار في ريف (هايتي).
We need to redirect cash flows
نحتاج لإعادة توجيه التدفقات النقدية
that are going now from the diaspora in the United States
الواردة من المغتربين في الولايات المتحدة
through Western Union wire transfers in cash
عبر تحويلات مصرفية نقدًا عن طريق (ويسترن يونيون)
directly into clean energy products
مباشرةً لمنتجات الطاقة النظيفة
that can be delivered to or picked up by their friends or family in Haiti.
التي يمكن إيصالها أو تسليمها إلى أصدقائهم أو عائلاتهم في (هايتي).
So the next time you hear about a technology or product
لذا في المرة التالية التي تسمعون فيها عن تكنولوجيا أو منتج
that's going to change the world,
تتجه إلى أن تغير العالم،
be a little bit skeptical.
كونوا أكثر حذرًا وتشككًا.
The inventor Dean Kamen, the guy who invented the Segway,
المخترع (دين كامين) الذي اخترع (سيجواي)،
a genius by any standards,
هو عبقري بكل المقاييس،
once said that his job is easy, inventing things is easy,
قال ذات مرة أن عمله سهل، اختراع الأشياء أمر سهل،
the hard part is the technology dissemination --
الجزء الأصعب هو نشر التكنولوجيا،
it's getting those technologies and products
وإيصال هذه التكنولوجيا والمنتجات
to the people who need it most.
إلى الأشخاص الذين يحتاجونها بشدة.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)